<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://joshuaebenezer.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://joshuaebenezer.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2026-02-11T05:15:17+00:00</updated><id>https://joshuaebenezer.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Joshua Peter Ebenezer</title><subtitle>Staff Research Engineer passionate about computational photography, video quality assessment, and deep learning. Currently at Samsung Research America. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Book List</title><link href="https://joshuaebenezer.github.io/blog/2026/what-im-reading/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Book List"/><published>2026-02-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-02-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://joshuaebenezer.github.io/blog/2026/what-im-reading</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://joshuaebenezer.github.io/blog/2026/what-im-reading/"><![CDATA[<p>I have a lot of interest in theology, philosophy, and history. I also read fiction sometimes. Here are some titles I have recently read and would recommend:</p> <h2 id="recently-read--recommended">Recently Read &amp; Recommended</h2> <p><strong>Dominion</strong> by Tom Holland</p> <p>The post-modern view that all worldviews are fundamentally the same is masterfully taken apart by agnostic historian Tom Holland, who almost grudgingly traces the history of Christianity and how it completely changed the moral compass of Western Civilization. What changed when an Empire that celebrated the death of slaves in arenas as entertainment began to worship a carpenter crucified? How did Christianity subsequently influence the trajectory of the world? Despite the general and perennial pessimism about the state of affairs in the world, I think Dominion presents the case for the Kingdom that has already been inaugarated but is yet to come.</p> <p><strong>War and Peace</strong> by Leo Tolstoy</p> <p>This took me all of 2025 to read. There are many themes in this book, but I think the one that really stood out to me was the simultaneous senselessness of war and the working of providence to direct human outcomes. Many actions in the Napoleonic Wars are attributed to individual brilliance and the tactics of generals, but Tolstoy shows how seemingly minor and random events changed the course of the war.</p> <p><strong>Crime and Punishment</strong> by Fyodor Dostoevsky</p> <p>What happens when you take utilitarianism and nihilism to its logical end? This powerful novel about how a young man tries to justify his murder of an old lady but is forced to confront the reality of sin, and finds redemption only through being drawn to confession by the influence of an impoverished prostitute who finds God. I found in this novel an allegory for the state of the human mind when made aware of its sinfulness. We try to make excuses for it but in the end we only find grace in confession and repentance.</p> <p><strong>“The City of God,”</strong> by Augustine</p> <p>Written as a rebuttal to Roman pagans who blamed Christians for Rome’s fall. This work is one of the earliest to emphasize that Christians identities are not defined by political affiliations, while also discussing frameworks for “Just War”. The Book also elucidates the Christian view of history as linear and guided by providence. There are some specific teachings I disagree with Augustine on, such as his particular interpretation of original sin and the conclusions he draws from it to support baptismal regeneration for infants.</p> <p><strong>The Brothers Karamazov</strong> by Fyodor Dostoevsky</p> <p>Dostoevsky’s magnum opus is a roller-coaster ride. Set in 19th century Russia, you might think this is just a murder mystery, but the murder mystery is a backdrop to a masterful exploration of human beliefs, human behavior, societal struggles, the rift between traditionalists and liberals, God, morality, love, and justice. One moment you are reading a conversation between the Spanish Inquisitor and Jesus, the next a love triangle unfolds, yet all of it comes together to create what is deservedly called one of the greatest works of literature ever produced.</p> <p><strong>Where the Crawdads Sing</strong> by Delia Owens</p> <p>A touching masterpiece. It is a coming-of-age story of a girl who lives in a marsh all by herself and has been dealt a tough hand in life. The novel strips away the veneer of civility that masks the brokenness of humans, and ultimately shows the redemptive power of love. Profoundly moving and a meditation on human nature.</p> <p><strong>7 Types of Atheism</strong> by John Gray</p> <p>Yes, there are that many! John Gray is an atheist himself and believes the most intellectually honest position an atheist can have is to acknowledge that there is no such thing as meaning or morality in life. There are several strands of atheism, ranging from the “new atheism” of the four horsemen to the humanists, who substitute humanity for God. Gray shows that the idea of atheism as “believing there is no God” only makes sense in the context of monotheistic faiths, and atheism has a much older and more complicated narrative.</p> <p><strong>The Reason for God</strong> by Timothy Keller</p> <p>Keller’s NY Times bestseller explores why belief in God still makes sense in the modern era. His arguments are aimed at humanists in particular, with emphasis on why God is necessary for making sense of human rights, morality, and liberal values. He presents numerous arguments from the cosmological to the teleological.</p> <p><strong>Sapiens</strong> by Yuval Noah Harari</p> <p>Harari’s take on human history is gripping, though much of his ideas on how society developed is speculation. His explanation of the rise of capitalism and the modern world order are praiseworthy, though his predictions of the future venture further into speculation. Well-written and thought-provoking despite its naturalistic presuppositions.</p> <p><strong>The Book Thief</strong> by Markus Zusak</p> <p>The story of a family in Germany harboring a Jew during World War II. The most interesting characteristic is its surprising and creative use of words and adjectives in unexpected ways. Touches on a range of human emotions with remarkable sensitivity.</p> <p><strong>Knowledge and Christian Belief</strong> by Alvin Plantinga</p> <p>Plantinga shows that almost all belief systems use circular reasoning. Much depends on the assumptions you begin with and your epistemology (how you think it’s possible to find truth). If you begin with humanistic assumptions, you arrive at humanistic conclusions. For a naturalist, there is no truth—only what is convenient for evolutionary advancement. For a Christian, humans are by nature fallen and cannot see spiritual truth unless moved by God. All else follows from these foundational assumptions.</p> <h2 id="currently-reading">Currently Reading</h2> <p>I am currently working through Augustine’s masterpiece <strong>“The City of God,”</strong> written as a rebuttal to Roman pagans who blamed Christians for Rome’s fall. This work also emphasizes that Christians belong not to any earthly city, and that our identities are not defined by political affiliations.</p> <h2 id="books-i-dont-recommend">Books I Don’t Recommend</h2> <p><strong>1984</strong> by George Orwell and <strong>The Master and Margarita</strong> by Mikhail Bulgakov deserve mention as classics I didn’t find compelling. Much of 1984’s content is widely known today as a consequence of the USSR’s fall, and much of the book reads as lecture rather than story. “The Master and Margarita” is a celebrated work of Russian literature, but much of its charm lies in its use of language, which doesn’t shine as clearly in English translation.</p> <h2 id="authors-who-shaped-my-thinking">Authors Who Shaped My Thinking</h2> <p>Several authors have profoundly shaped my worldview:</p> <ul> <li><strong>C.S. Lewis</strong> — on faith, reason, and human nature</li> <li><strong>Augustine</strong> — and Augustinian theology through Calvin, John Piper, and R.C. Sproul</li> <li><strong>Philip Yancey</strong> — on grace and redemption</li> </ul> <h2 id="childhood-reading">Childhood Reading</h2> <p>When younger, I completed Enid Blyton’s Secret Seven and Famous Five series—highly recommended for school-age readers. I also worked through Agatha Christie’s Miss Marple and Hercule Poirot series, and the Perry Mason mystery series. Excellent detective fiction for light, engaging reads.</p> <hr/> <p><strong>What are you reading?</strong> I’d love to hear recommendations or discuss books. Feel free to reach out via <a href="mailto:joshuapeterebenezer@gmail.com">email</a> or connect on <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/joshua-peter-ebenezer">LinkedIn</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="reading"/><category term="theology"/><category term="philosophy"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Books that have shaped my thinking on theology, philosophy, history, and faith]]></summary></entry></feed>